welcome to meditating with John Breaux
Vicki I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto my study mindfulness and
mindfulness practices and related
phenomena like Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience
higher states of consciousness the
cultivation of wisdom we've also been
practicing the pasta meditation meta
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan Chacon for
over 29 years I've been teaching them
for almost professional if almost 20
years this is a course if you're joining
us for the first time you're of course
welcome to stay but you should know that
we there's been a series of lessons
every Monday is Dharma day I teach a new
principle that builds on the previous
principles and usually give people a
practical exercise so they can get an
experiential understanding of that if
you go to the notes for this video
you'll see links to previous lessons and
also to previous six Tuesday through
Friday or during today we meet together
we sit sometimes I do a bit of review
but at the end of every day Monday
through Friday there's a Q&A session the
Q&A sessions Tuesday through Friday tend
to be a little bit longer so a couple of
announcements
remember that for Cutie's for today
whatever we're doing said please limit
them to questions about the practice if
you have more general questions and I
welcome them you know about the
cultivation of wisdom responding to the
meaning crisis relationship between
Buddhism and other wisdom traditions
like stoicism how does Coggs I interact
with this kind of thing all of that is
welcome and what we do is we have a live
streaming Q&A once every month we're
doing it this Friday be on YouTube there
will be at 3 p.m. est um so I think
that's everything we need in order to
get ready please get yourself into
your posture remember to always find the
core for perhaps today you're doing the
past no or meta or maybe another
instance of meditative questioning
meditative questing so you're posed to
do not disturb and we will begin
everyone when I say begin begin
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition coming out
of the set is part of the practice so
I'll just see if there are perhaps any
questions we did a lot of extra
questions yesterday so perhaps any
questions right now so a reminder that
on Monday we'll be doing the second part
of the two part on the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness vigilance
sensitivity acutest curity noticing and
reminding and I'll be teaching you there
how to deal with distractions and with
hindrances here's a question from
stringer
hey this is from Germany my question is
which videos from your YouTube channel
are most conducive to better
understanding of the meta practice
we're frozen
yeah
yeah hello
oh yeah community
can you hear me now yeah sorry for that
it's like technical glitch technology is
the God that limps or reread the
question from Strutter from Germany hey
hey this is from Germany my question is
which videos from your YouTube channel
are most conducive to a better
understanding of the meta practice I
believe its episodes 9 and 10 and 11
where I'm talking about consciousness
and higher states of consciousness and I
talk about the relationship between
meditation and scaling down and
contemplation and scaling up I believe
it's those ones I'll double check and if
I'm if I misremembered
will put the correct links in the note
descriptions this is from Matt Boehner
is it sensible to use the technique of
meditative questioning to explore the
root of certain feelings or emotions I
sometimes find it hard to place why I
feel a certain way so it this isn't this
is a tricky question to answer
the meditative questioning is a good way
to meditate into it try to see deeply
into why you're doing this what I mean
is why you're doing a particular form of
behavior or experiencing a particular
kind of emotion so it is a wise thing to
do but there's there's a risk to it and
I mentioned this last time when we turn
this from the act of deepening the
process to a technique for producing a
particular price result a particular
answer we are training our brain
ultimately in the wrong way so I would
recommend if you're going to do what
you're suggesting that you set it aside
at a different time from your regular
practice in a different location and you
do not make it a regular thing to use
meditative questioning to get these
kinds of differences so I wouldn't say
don't ever do it
but mark it off very clearly and
explicitly two more
processing parts of your brain that this
is not the normal practice I'm not going
to do this regularly so that they don't
get fused and that you lose what the
meditative questioning is supposed to be
doing for you
Calico image I'm finding that as the
weeks of practice have gone by if I may
miss one day that I find an emotional
rising of anxiousness is these too much
of an attachment to the new meditative
experience I don't know of attachments
the right word and what what happens is
and again you know it's difficult when I
don't know a lot of you personally but
generally what happens as you start
think of the word habit its relate to
you it's related to inhabit all right
how about in habit right as you start to
let this process habit you deeply and
you inhabit the world that it starts to
disclose for you right it starts to
become very starts to become a habit
until you I have it was originally the
cloak worn by a monk somebody dedicated
to spiritual transformation by the way
right that what you'll get is you'll
start to shift where this is certain to
become your second nature which is what
you want and then if you don't do the
practice I experienced this very deeply
if I don't do my practice for the day
because something has happened or
perhaps I'm too ill but that's a
potentially confounding variable let's
say something gets up there's an
emergency I don't get to get to my
practice properly I feel it throughout
the day I feel it throughout the day
because I'm no longer inhabiting the
world of the being mode the world of
waking up so I don't think you're
getting too attached I think you're
coming to actually inhabit the
mindfulness way of being
Carolyn white how to navigate
uncomfortable physical sensations as
they rise tightness in the belly do I
simply note it and move forward with my
focus yes Carolyn do that for now notice
it and move on with your practice but on
Monday I will on Dharma day I wish i
teach you how to actually deal with
those kinds of distractions we'll talk
about physical distractions emotional
distractions mental distractions why
three lines for ruining I don't know
this is from Dennis I've never been
given an explanation so you're asking me
to sort of offer a conjecture here I
surmise that what's happening is we and
this has to do this comes from a more
from car design we have an embodied
existence in which we Orient and because
we're bodied we have if we have in front
of me behind me orientation and then we
have a up and down orientation that runs
right through our center of gravity and
therefore by doing those three lines
we're massively engaging the sort of
fundamental fields our embodiment sets
out for us in perspective the kind of
perspectives we have and the way we are
oriented in space so I think that's the
reason why the three lines probably
evolved I have no evidence for this I'm
I'm offering you a conjecture based on
what I know from the phenomenology of
embodiment that comes from what's called
for cognitive science under a fair how
can i distinguish if I'm in the right
state meaning not following asleep but
being the middle of the usual States
today I have felt like falling asleep
but not missing out on the counting etc
so again you should feel quite alert in
the practice what that means is that the
states here that sort of you're you're
stable so you're not your mind isn't
rushing but there's a sensitivity
there's an alertness there's right
there's that empowering of vigilance
there's a sense of the mind becoming
more engaged with reality as opposed to
when we're falling asleep where we're
losing alertness the the sense that that
insight is imminent
for us it's away we get a kind of
contentedness things right the sense of
growth and change is diminishing and the
scope and engagement of the mind tends
to also diminish and so that's how you
can learn to try and track between
falling asleep and what we're all trying
to do the Buddha the awakened one and
wake up think about use that metaphor
what's happening in your mind when
you're waking up not not when you're
starting to play in your day there's all
the rushing worry but that actual shift
that felt change in consciousness as
you're waking up you're sort of
initially dozy and then there's that
brightening the opening the engagement
the seeking for reap the contact with
reality so everyone thank you very much
for joining I want to thank my dear
friend and techno major Mara my beloved
son Jason please subscribe to my channel
to be notified at the next video you
will also find on my channel the
awakening for the meaning crisis series
a lot of other videos my voices with big
bay key discussion with people who are
trying to bridge between science and
spirituality and renew the cultivation
of wisdom in our time and so there's a
lot of material on there that's relevant
to a lot of the topics we discuss in
this course and also for encompassing it
and any more a broader more encompassing
way of life in the cultivation of wisdom
and ultimately ultimately other than
what we need to do for our survival what
we most need to cultivate now is a
growth in wisdom please share this video
series the meditation classes with other
people that you think might benefit I'm
doing this to help others and I'm asking
you to help me to help as many people as
I can
we'll be doing this every weekday at
9:30 est and remember one more time
there's the general Q&A this Friday at 3
p.m. est
thank you very much for your time and
attention please keep meditating
contemplating and flowing take care
everyone